A Guide to the Virginia Dental Association records, 1870-1985
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Virginia Dental Association records 1870-2011, bulk 1870-1985
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
88/Jul/17
27 linear feet.
Virginia Dental Association
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Virginia Dental Association, 1988 and 1989.
Accruals
Included in these records are issues of the Virginia Dental Journal which have been printed since the last gift in 1989.
Biographical/Historical Information
On November 3, 1870 nine Virginia dentists met in Richmond to establish an organization to "cultivate the science and the art of dentistry, and all its collateral branches, to elevate and sustain the professional character of dentists; and to promote amongst them mutual improvement, social intercourse and good will." This meeting marked the creation of the Virginia Dental Association (VDA) or the Virginia State Dental Association as it was named when first created. The VDA changed to its current name in 1970. The VDA was the successor to the first professional dental organization, the Virginia Society of Surgeon Dentists which was formed in 1842.
An early goal of the VDA was to create standards and regulations for the profession. When the VDA was formed there were no statutes regulating the practice of dentistry in Virginia. The VDA spent several years drafting a bill to present to the state legislature culminating in the passage of the Dental Act of 1886. This act also established the Virginia Board of Dental Examiners. The VDA also successfully campaigned in 1915 to have a representative on the State Board of Health making Virginia the first state to include a dentist on such a board. In 1936 the VDA helped pass a bill that outlawed advertising dental services and prices as a means of protecting the public from unethical dental practices. This remained in effect until the early 1980s when the Federal Trade Commission ruled that truthful advertising could not be restricted.
Dental education was another subject of much interest and debate for the VDA. They supported the creation of the first dental school in Virginia in 1893 at the University College of Medicine (UCM). In 1913, UCM merged with the Medical College of Virginia (MCV), which had created its own dental school in 1897. For a time some members of the VDA thought that dentist should obtain an MD degree to practice medicine. The Dental Act only required a diploma and a certificate from the state board to practice dentistry. A dental degree was not required to sit for the state board exam. A law requiring an MD was passed in 1910, but was repealed in 1914 before any provisions were enacted.
The VDA, which is a component of the American Dental Association, created component societies in 1931. This was to better facilitate communication and professional development for member dentists throughout the state. Dentists who joined a component society also became members of the state and national associations through this tripartite structure. Virginia was divided into eight regions. Each region was arranged to have an existing local society within the area to become the component group where applicable. This arrangement is still in place today. The component societies are:
Component 1, Virginia Tidewater Dental Association, founded 1880
Component 2, Peninsula Dental Society, founded 1934
Component 3, Southside Dental Society, founded 1925
Component 4, Richmond Dental Society, founded 1894
Component 5, Piedmont Dental Society, founded 1916
Component 6, Southwest Virginia Dental Society, founded 1917
Component 7, Shenandoah Valley Dental Association, founded 1914
Component 8, Northern Virginia Dental Society, founded 1931
The VDA began publishing its journal the Bulletin of the Virginia State Dental Association in 1923. After sporadic publication for the first ten years the VDA began publishing on a regular schedule. The number of issues published has varied from three to six. The journal is currently published quarterly. The title changed to the Virginia Dental Journal in 1964. It is a resource for members to find information about professional and scientific developments, legislative issues, and annual meetings. The journal also includes editorials and news updates from the component societies.
An annual meeting of the VDA was held for members to come together and benefit from the mutual exchange of ideas and practical knowledge. The meetings offered an opportunity to focus on issues such as professional ethics, dental legislation, public health and service, and education. Much of the work of the organization was carried out by committees all of which were overseen by the governing body the Executive Council. The VDA had three elected officers the president, the president-elect, and the secretary-treasurer as well as several appointed officers including the editor of the journal. The VDA did not have a headquarters until the organization hired its first executive secretary in 1964 and she set up the headquarters in her home. Since that time it has been located in several areas around Richmond. Today the VDA is governed by a board of directors and still holds an annual meeting. The VDA continues to help improve the profession and its members, support dental education, promote public dental health, and provide outreach services to underserved populations.
Scope and Content
The records of the Virginia Dental Association (VDA) 1870-2011, provide insight into the changes in the dental profession and also the evolution of professional organizations in general.The materials include the official minutes and proceedings of the organization as well as committee records, component society materials, correspondence, financial records, annual meeting records and programs, membership records, subject files, materials relating to the American Dental Association and other national, state, and local dental organizations, and research files used to write One Hundred Years of Dentistry in Virginia.
Series 1: Annual Compilation of Records, 1870-1972. This series, divided into two subseries, consists of the official minutes of the VDA and the records of the Executive Council, the main governing body of the organization.
Subseries 1.1: Minute Books, 1870-1963. The minute books contain annual meeting programs and proceedings, speeches and papers delivered at the meetings, the Bulletin the official publication of the VDA, committee reports, financial statements, newspaper clippings, member lists, and meeting attendee lists including guests and exhibitors. Also included in the minute books are reports from the Bureau of Dental Heath which often contains statistics regarding race and schools where clinics were held and reports of the State Board of Dental Examiners which include statistics regarding applicants for dental licenses.
Subseries 1.2: Executive Council Records, 1931-1972, bulk 1962-1972. These records include meeting minutes and reports along with some correspondence.
Series 2: Financial Records, 1887-1975. These records include bank statements and deposits, invoices, proposed budgets, receipts, and treasurer's books.
Series 3: Committees, 1924-1979. This series contains materials such as correspondence and reports of various standing and special committees.
Series 4: Annual Meetings, 1924-1980. This series includes materials related to the planning and execution of the meetings and is divided into four subseries.
Subseries 4.1: Annual Meeting Records, 1929-1980. This subseries contains general records such as correspondence, financial information, and publicity related to the planning of each annual meeting. Some files also include the proceedings for the meeting as well. The planning for most meetings began one to two years prior to the event, which is indicated by the inclusive date range listed for each folder.
Subseries 4.2: Local Arrangements and Program Committees, 1929-1939, 1954-1956, 1965. Materials in this subseries include correspondence and planning information related to arrangements for clinics, programs, and entertainment at the annual meetings.
Subseries 4.3: Programs, 1924-1970. This subseries contains copies of the official meeting programs.
Subseries 4.4: Meeting Exhibitors, 1927-1980. This subseries includes correspondence with vendors of dental related products and services requesting that the vendors purchase exhibit space or buy advertisements in the meeting program.
Series 5: Correspondence, 1917-1985. This series is divided into two subseries.
Subseries 5.1: General VDA Correspondence, 1917-1975. This subseries consists mostly of correspondence between the membership and the officers of the VDA. There is also some correspondence with the ADA, other state dental societies, the Virginia State Health Department, Virginia Board of Dental Examiners, and other state offices. The subjects most often covered include dues (overdue notices and disputes), issues related to the governance and structure of the VDA, meeting planning (locations, exhibitors, entertainment, and programs), legislative issues related to dentistry, and professional ethics issues (advertising, obligations to public health, etc).
Subseries 5.2: Officers' Correspondence and Related Materials, 1927-1985. These files consist primarily of specific VDA officers' correspondence. Additionally, some files also include speeches, photographs, and clippings.
Series 6: Component Societies, 1931-1978. This series contains materials such as correspondence, membership lists, and meeting programs from the eight component societies in Virginia.
Series 7: Administrative Files, 1919-1984. This series consists of subject and court files and is divided into two subseries.
Subseries 7:1: Subject Files, 1919-1984. Contains various subject files relating to legislative and professional issues, membership benefits such as insurance and retirement plans, and other materials such as newspaper clippings and photographs. Also includes membership card files kept by the VDA.
Subseries 7.2: Federal Trade Commission Case, 1960-1978. This subseries pertains to the Federal Trade Commission complaint against the American Dental Association and several of its constituent groups including the Virginia Dental Association and the Northern Virginia Dental Society (American Dental Association, et. al., Docket No. 9093). The FTC complaint stated that the ADA ethical codes violated antitrust laws by barring advertising and preventing price competition. Part of the defense strategy was to prove that the VDA and the NVDS were non-profit groups and as such were outside the FTC's jurisdiction. Documents in this subseries include Children's Dental Health Week materials, public service brochures promoting dental care, newspaper clipping discussing community outreach programs by the VDA, and materials on the governance and benefits of the two groups.
Series 8: National and State Dental Organizations, 1923-1976. This series contains materials such as correspondence, brochures, and newsletters from various other dental organizations including the American Dental Association, several local Virginia dental clubs, and some out-of-state dental groups.
Series 9: One Hundred Years of Dentistry in Virginia, 1873-1969. This series contains essays, speeches, research notes, photographs and related materials that were compiled to write this history. Research materials were collected primarily by Hermie Wait Powell, the author, and Dr. William Newton Hodgkins
Series 10: VDA Journals, 1928-2011. This series contains an incomplete set of the Bulletin and the Virginia Dental Journal. There are eight bound volumes of the Bulletin, loose issues of the Virginia Dental Journal from 1976-1983, 2008-2009, and 2011, and a DVD with the electronic version from 2004-2008. To view the current issue of the journal visit their website. Membership is required to view the journals on the website.
Arrangement
The records of the Virginia Dental Association have been divided into ten series with subseries as needed. Efforts have been made to preserve the original arrangement of these files where applicable.
Series 1: Annual Compilation of Records, 1870-1972
Subseries 1.1: Minute Books, 1870-1963
Subseries 1.2: Executive Council Records, 1931-1972, bulk 1962-1972
Series 2: Financial Records, 1887-1975
Series 3: Committees, 1924-1979
Series 4: Annual Meetings, 1929-1980
Subseries 4.1: Annual Meeting Records, 1929-1980
Subseries 4.2: Local Arrangements and Program Committee Records, 1929-1939, 1954-1956, 1965
Subseries 4.3: Programs, 1924-1970
Subseries 4.4: Meeting Exhibitors, 1927-1980
Series 5: Correspondence, 1917-1985
Subseries 5.1: General VDA Correspondence, 1917-1975
Subseries 5.2: Officer's Correspondence and Related Materials, 1924-1985
Series 6: Component Societies, 1931-1978
Series 7: Administrative Files, 1919-1984
Subseries 7.1: Subject Files, 1919-1977
Subseries 7.2: Federal Trade Commission Case, 1960-1978
Series 8: National and State Dental Organizations, 1923-1976
Series 9: One Hundred Years of Dentistry in Virginia, 1873-1963
Series 10: VDA Journals, 1928-2011
Contents List
- Annual Compilation of Records 1870-1972 (Box 1-18)
  - Minute Books, 1870-1963 (Box 1-17)
    - Minute Books 1870-1915 (Box 1)
      Contains six minute books: 1870-1877, 1878-1892, 1893-1903, 1904-1905, 1906-1911, and 1912-1915
    - Minute Books, 1916-1917, 1918-1919, 1920, and 1921 (Box-folder 2:1-4)
    - Minute Books, 1922, 1923, and 1924 (Box-folder 3:1-3)
      The 1922 minutes mention that three women dentists were admitted into the VDA for the first time.
    - Minute Books, 1925 and 1926 (Box-folder 4:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1927, 1928, and 1929 (Box-folder 5:1-3)
    - Minute Books, 1930, 1931, and 1932 (Box-folder 6:1-3)
      At the 1932 annual meeting Martin Dewey, president of the ADA, discussed the lack of black dentists and also issues regarding dentists working with the Native American population.
    - Minute Books, 1933, 1934, and 1935 (Box-folder 7:1-3)
    - Minute Books, 1936, 1937, and 1938 (Box-folder 8:1-3)
      The 1936 minutes contain letters from other Virginia dental groups, including the Old Dominion Dental Society (the separate organization for black dentists), regarding support for legislation to outlaw advertising dentists.
    - Minute Books, 1939, 1940, and 1941 (Box-folder 9:1-3)
    - Minute Books, 1942 and 1943 (Box-folder 10:1-2)
      The 1942 annual meeting marked the centennial celebration of organized dentistry in Virginia. The minutes include a resolution by the Committee on Tire Priorities for the Richmond Dental Society authorizing the VDA to work to have dentists given priority rating for automobile tires; a presentation by M.S. McClung of the Office of Price Control discussing the need for price control during war time; and Dr. Harry Bear's discussion of the accelerated program at the Medical College of Virginia, School of Dentistry for those persons who join the Army or Navy reserves during World War II.
    - Minute Books, 1944-1946 and 1947-1948 (Box-folder 11:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1949-1950 and 1951-1952 (Box-folder 12:1-2)
      During the 1952 meeting the president, J.H. Cocks, discussed civil defense training for dentists in the case of atomic attack. He also recommended the next president appoint a committee to study racial segregation as it concerned membership in the VDA.
    - Minute Books, 1953-1954 and 1955 (Box-folder 13:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1956 and 1957 (Box-folder 14:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1958 and 1959 (Box-folder 15:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1960 and 1961 (Box-folder 16:1-2)
    - Minute Books, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 17:1-2)
  - Executive Council, 1931-1972, bulk 1962-1972 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence and Meeting Minutes, 1931-1957 (Box-folder 18:1)
    - Correspondence and Meeting Minutes, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 18:2)
      Several documents from 1962 discuss the inclusion of blacks in the VDA membership.
    - Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 18:3-10)
- Financial Records, 1887-1975 (Box 18-19)
  - Audits, 1926, 1930, 1933, 1937, 1940, 1953-1954, 1956-1958, 1962, and 1970-1975 (Box-folder 18:11-12)
  - Bank Statements and Deposits, 1926-1940 (Box-folder 18:13)
  - Invoices, 1927-1935 (Box-folder 18:14-15)
  - Petty Expense Account, 1927 (Box-folder 18:16)
  - Proposed Budgets, 1956, 1959, and 1960-1964 (Box-folder 18:17)
  - Receipts, 1923-1939 (Box-folder 18:18)
  - Remittance and Refunds, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 18:19)
  - Treasurer's Books, 1887-1935 (Box-folder 19:1-5)
- Committees, 1924-1979 (Box 19-21)
  - Advisory Committee to Dental Assistants, 1961-1974 (Box-folder 19:6)
  - Advisory Committee to Dental Hygienists, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 19:7)
  - Advisory, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 19:8)
  - Budget, 1961-1972 (Box-folder 19:9)
  - Cancer, 1962-1972 (Box-folder 19:10)
  - Centennial, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 19:11)
  - Cleft Palate, 1956-1963 (Box-folder 19:12)
  - Clinic, 1934-1939, 1956-1962 (Box-folder 19:13)
  - Committee Chairmen Handbook, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 19:14)
  - Committee Lists, 1924-1932, 1954-1957, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 19:15)
  - Component Presidents (Advisory), 1955-1956 (Box-folder 19:16)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1961-1972 (Box-folder 19:17)
  - Continuing Education, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 19:18)
  - Accounts, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 19:19)
    This committee was formerly known as Mouth Hygiene.
  - Clippings and Reprints, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 19:20)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1964 (Box-folder 19:21-23)
  - Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 19:24-32)
  - Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 20:1-6)
  - Membership, 1955-1957, 1962 (Box-folder 20:7)
  - Newsletter, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 20:8)
  - Suggested Plan for Parent-Teacher Association Meeting on Dental Health, undated (Box-folder 20:9)
  - Dental Care for the Elderly and Indigent, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 20:10)
  - Dental Care Programs, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 20:11)
  - Dental Education, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 20:12)
  - Dental Health, 1953, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 20:13)
  - Dental Hygienist Course, 1954, 1956, 1958 (Box-folder 20:14)
  - Dental Service Corporation, 1963-1972 (Box-folder 20:15)
  - Dental Society Review, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 20:16)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 20:17-18)
  - Minutes, Reports, and Related Documents, 1959-1972 (Box-folder 20:19)
  - Disease Prevention, 1974 (Box-folder 20:20)
  - Districts, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 20:21)
  - Emergency Dental Relief Work, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 20:22)
    This committee was formed as a result of the Depression-era Federal Emergency Relief Administration. The committee worked with the state Emergency Relief Administration to set a fee scale for dental work performed for the unemployed.
  - Entertainment, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 20:23)
  - Executive, 1929-1934, 1956-1971 (Box-folder 20:24)
  - Financial Investments, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 20:25)
  - History, 1953-1971 (Box-folder 20:26)
  - Hospital Dental Service, 1953-1972 (Box-folder 20:27)
  - Hospitalization Insurance Program, 1956 (Box-folder 20:28)
  - Hygiene, 1924 (Box-folder 20:29)
  - Insurance, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 20:30)
  - International Relations, 1965-1977 (Box-folder 20:31)
  - Joint Committee of Representatives MCV & VDA, 1929 (Box-folder 20:32)
  - Journal Editorial Staff, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 20:33)
  - Legislative, 1929-1936, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 20:34-36)
  - Legislative, 1960-1972 (Box-folder 21:1-4)
  - Liaison Committee of VDA and State Dental Laboratories Association, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 21:5)
  - Liaison Representative to the Virginia Association of Professionals, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 21:6)
  - Liaison Representative to 5th District ADA, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 21:7)
  - Lyons Testimonial Dinner, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 21:8)
    This committee arranged a testimonial dinner at the annual meeting to honor Dr. Harry Lyons and his leadership as president of the American Dental Association.
  - Applications, 1927-1934 (Box-folder 21:9)
  - General, 1929-1937, 1954 (Box-folder 21:10)
  - Lists, 1926-1927, 1935-1937, and 1960 (Box-folder 21:11)
  - Questionnaires, 1950s (Box-folder 21:12)
    The questionnaire includes full name, date of birth, name of colleges attended and degrees earned, date of admission to the association, veteran status and rank held, and any offices held in the association at the component and state levels.
  - Student Declaration Blanks, 1936 (Box-folder 21:13)
  - Military Affairs, 1956, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 21:14)
  - Mouthguard, 1960s (Box-folder 21:15)
  - Mouth Hygiene, 1929-1935 (Box-folder 21:16-17)
    The Mouth Hygiene committee became the Council on Dental Health in 1948. Folder 17 includes educational posters that were created to promote dental health.
  - Necrology, 1935-1937, 1954-1963 (Box-folder 21:18)
  - Prosthetic Dental Services, 1953 (Box-folder 21:19)
  - Student Advisory Committee, 1953 (Box-folder 21:20)
  - Public Information, 1966-1974 (Box-folder 21:21)
  - Relief, 1933-1936 and 1953-1970 (Box-folder 21:22-24)
  - Special, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 21:25)
    This file contains reports from several special committees including Constitution and Bylaws, Collection of Amalgam Scraps, and a committee to study the feasibility of hiring an executive secretary for the Association.
  - Society of Esteemed Dentists, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 21:26)
  - State Institutions, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 21:27)
  - Student Loan and Scholarship, 1966-1976 (Box-folder 21:28)
- Annual Meetings, 1924-1980 (Box 21-24)
  - Annual Meeting Records, 1929-1980 (Box 21-22)
    - 1929 Annual Meeting, 1929 (Box-folder 21:29)
    - 1932 Annual Meeting, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 21:30)
    - 1939 Annual Meeting, Proceedings 1939 (Box-folder 21:31)
    - 1955 Annual Meeting, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 21:32)
      This meeting was a convention cruise to Havana and Nassau.
    - 1959 Annual Meeting, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 21:33)
    - 1963 Annual Meeting, Proceedings, 1963 (Box-folder 21:34)
    - 1964 Annual Meeting 1961-1964 (Box-folder 22:1)
    - 1965 Annual Meeting 1963-1965 (Box-folder 22:2-4)
    - 1966 Annual Meeting 1964-1966 (Box-folder 22:5-7)
      Two meetings were held in 1966. The first was a convention cruise to San Juan and St. Thomas. The second meeting was held in Norfolk. Materials include registration cards and passenger lists for the cruise in addition to the general correspondence and other materials related to the planning of the meetings.
    - 1967 Annual Meeting, Publicity 1967 (Box-folder 22:8)
    - 1968 Annual Meeting, Publicity, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 22:9)
    - 1969 Annual Meeting, Publicity, 1969 (Box-folder 22:10)
    - 1971 Annual Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 22:11-13)
      Folder 13 contains several photographs of the banquet.
    - 1972 Annual Meeting, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 22:14)
    - 1974 Annual Meeting, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 22:15)
    - 1975 Annual Meeting, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 22:16-17)
    - 1976 Annual Meeting, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 22:18)
    - 1977 Annual Meeting, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 23:1-3)
    - 1978 Annual Meeting, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 23:4-6)
    - 1979 Annual Meeting, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 23:7-9)
    - 1980 Annual Meeting, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 23:10-12)
  - Local Arrangements and Program Committee Records 1929-1939, 1954-1956, 1965 (Box 23-24)
    - 1929 Local Arrangements, 1929 (Box-folder 23:13)
    - 1930 Local Arrangements, 1930 (Box-folder 23:14)
    - 1935 Local Arrangements, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 23:15)
    - 1929 Program Committee, 1929 (Box-folder 23:16)
      Includes samples of meeting badges from several vendors
    - 1930 Program Committee, 1930 (Box-folder 23:17)
    - 1931 Program Committee, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 23:18)